<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of publique reformation of a church</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10563</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20834.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23247674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23247674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10563)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1802:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of publique reformation of a church</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge, England? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:26440:1"/>
            <head>OF PVBLIQVE REFORMATION OF A CHVRCH.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of this Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formation
we are to
know
<list>
                     <item>What it is. This reformation is a bringing of men back vnto God, by puting away euil, and by renewing the performance of all holy dueties decayed, eſpecially in the publique ſocieties of Gods children. 2.
Chron 19. 4, 2. Chron. 34. 35. 2. King. 18. 4. 23. 4. 20. 2. Kings 23. 21. 2. Chron. 29 3, 25. 30. 30. per totum. 31. 2. ad finem.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie
of it,
which may
appeare
<list>
                     <item>1 By the commanundement of the Lord, not only exacting of euery ſee man repentance (whereof this is a moſt ſolemne kinde) but alſo geuing charge for this matter, Ier. 7. 23, 24, 1. King. 18. 36
Pſalme 2.</item>
                     <item>2 By the extraordinarie miniſterie of Prophets, and other perſons when God ſo often reyſed vp, taught, and aſſiſted extraordinarilie, that they might be his inſtruments to bring men again to God
and to reforme things amiſſe. Which extraordinarie worke if the Lord, done for the reformation of his Church, declareth the neceſſitie of it.</item>
                     <item>3 By the fearefull plagues which God brought vpon the neglectors of reformation. Eli, becauſe he reclaimed not his ſonnes, and ſo the people which for the great iniquitie of the young men
abhorred the offering of the Lord, loſt the Prieſthoode, and make his necke. The young men alſo periſhed in a great ſlaughter of the people. 1. Sam. 2. &amp; 4 Ioaſh and his people, becauſe they
would not obey the word of the Lord in the mouth of Zachariah, to reforme that which was amiſſe, were forſaken of the Lord, and deliuered into the hands of their enemies. 2. Chron. 24. 20. 25
For this cauſe the people of Amaziah fell before Ioaſh. Ieruſalem was ſacked, the king himſelfe taken priſoner, and afterward ſlaine by treaſon. 2. Chron. 25. 16. 23. 24. 27.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3 The parts
of this refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
which are
<list>
                     <item>1 Suppreſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ng of euery idolatrous, ſuperſtitious, filthy and ſtrange hind, doctrine, office, vſe, or ceremonie remayning. Wherein heede muſt be taken, that no remnant of the aforeſaid be ſuffered to
contunie, becauſe ſuch remnants prouoke God to anger, and were alwaies hurtfull to the Church. Iudg. 8. 27. 2. Chron. 20. 23.</item>
                     <item>2 Conforming and reducing of the whole ſtate of the Church, that is to ſay, of the doctrine, officers, forme of gouernment, order &amp;c. of it, to their auntient integritie: that is, to the preſcription of
the word, or of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, wherby the Church was firſt eſtabliſhed. See the 5. point. 2. Kings 23. 24. 2. Chron. 29. 25.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>4 The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
who are
to work this
reformation,
which are
theſe.
<list>
                     <item>1 The author &amp; efficient cauſe of reformations God himſelfe. Eſai 62. 7. who if he turne not the hearts of men to obey his ſeruants perſwading to reformation it is becauſe hee mindeth to deſtroy
them. 2. Chron. 25. 16. 20. 1. Sam. 2. 25. Pro. 21. 12.</item>
                     <item>2 The inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
wh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord hath
ſanctified for
this worke,
theſe are
<list>
                           <item>1 The prince
whoſe due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
is
<list>
                                 <item>1 To call and compell both miniſters and people to returne to the ordinances of the Lord, ſet down in his word 2. Kings 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>. 2. Ch<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>on. 29. 4. 5, 15.</item>
                                 <item>2 To be himſelfe formoſt in the pra<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>iſe of publique actions of godlines, that his example may <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>ere vp and ſtrengthen other. 2. Sam. 6. 2. 5. 15. 16. 2. Kings 23. 2. 3.</item>
                                 <item>3 To make lawes for the co<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap> of reformation. 2. Chron. 15. 13.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 The mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters,
to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
it belongs
<list>
                                 <item>1 To pray earneſtly and contenually into the Lord, for the ſetting vp and reforming of his Church. Eſay. 62. 7</item>
                                 <item>2 To make knowen the word of Gain that behalfe to the Prince and people. 2. Kings 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>. 8. Exod. 4. 14 &amp; 5. 1.</item>
                                 <item>3 To ioyne with the people, and to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>oe before them in all their ſuites to them in authoritie, for reformation. Eſay. 62. 10. Exod. 4. &amp; 5.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 So many of the people, eſpecially of the Elders, know the will of God, to whom it belongeth not onely to ioyne in prayers is God for the good of his people. Heſt. 4. 16. but
alſo in prayer and godlines to ioyne in this ſun with the miniſters. 1. Kings 18. 30. Exod. 3. 18. and at the Princes commandement to deface the monuments of idolatrie. 2. Kin.
11 18. 10. 27.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>5 The rule and ſquere
whereby the
ſeruantes of
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord muſt
perform this
reformation,
which is the
word onely,
of which we
are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<list>
                     <item>1 The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
why the
word is to be
uſed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
rule of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
which are
<list>
                           <item>Firſt, ſeeing to reforme a church is nothing els buthe renewing of the firſt building and beautie of it, and by the word only it was firſt built vp &amp; beautified: therfore by it alſo it muſt
be reformed.</item>
                           <item>Secondly, foraſmuch as the redreſſing of euery mus ſeuerall wayes is to be performed by the word. Pſal. 11 9. a whole church cannot otherwiſe be reformed.</item>
                           <item>Thirdly, ſith the Lord reprouing the vngodly for haing, reformation, verifieth it hereby, becauſe they caſt his lawes behind their backs, Pſal. 50. it cannot be auoyded but the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of a church is to be deruied from the word.</item>
                           <item>4 By the examples of ſuch as at the commandement of God, haue either accompliſhed or laboured any ſuch reformation, who alwayes haue brought and called men to the rules of the
word of God. 2. Kings 23. 2. 3. Nehem. 8. 1. 2. 3. 4. Nehem. 10. 29. Gal. 6. 16. Reuel. 3. 3</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The man
not how to
vſe this rule
aright wher
men are to
obſerue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in
<list>
                           <item>Aboliſhing things they muſt iudge by the word, whats idolatrous, what ſuperſtitious, what ſtrange or crept in without warrant from the Lord. &amp;c. and ſo to aboliſh them.</item>
                           <item>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming.
if it be
<list>
                                 <item>In matters
of diſcipline,
<list>
                                       <item>1 Where expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes
of Chriſt,
and examples of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
are found.
<list>
                                             <item>1 They muſt carefully marke of theſe commaundements and examples, which are tempora<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                                   <desc>•…</desc>
                                                </gap> and extraordinarie, which otherwiſe</item>
                                             <item>2 They muſt embrace and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                                                   <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                                </gap>, without gaineſaying and condictious that which is ordinarie, not onely as the beſt, but as the
onely true and allowed ordinances of the Lord, leauing the extraordinarie things to the Lord, or whole only power it is to break
the ordinarie rules of his word.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2 Where expreſſe direction i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap> not found, as in ſome matters of order, and other circumſtances, they muſt take heed that they admit<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap> nothing which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
to the generall rules <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>f order, comelines, and edification ſet down in the word.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>In doctrine likewiſe, where expreſſe and laſting rules are found, they muſt receiue them as the vndoubted Oracles of God: where any thing is in queſtion that hath not ſuch
pla<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                                       <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                    </gap>es they muſt order and determine euery matter by the analogie of faith.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>6 The aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarie
eude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors
againſt
in where we
are to note
the wilines
of Sathan,
which hath a
ſeuerall
charmeta
bring a ſleep
it it may be,
euery one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
hath any
hand in the
worke, as for
the
<list>
                     <item>1 Prince, he
putteth into
his head by
flattering
courtiers, &amp;c.
<list>
                           <item>1 That theſe ſeekers of reformation entend of ſtrengthen themſelues, that they may the better rebell againſt him. Nehem. 2. 9. whereas the ende of reformation is, that no diſobedient
perſon may he ſuffered. Rom. 13. 1. and reformation hath neuer ſuffered men to rebell againſt the enemies of it, how much leſſe wil it againſt the friends?</item>
                           <item>2 That ſuch exquiſite reformation wil make <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>, and withdraw the people from following their vocations. Exod. 5. 4. wheras contrariwiſe, reformation cannot away with any
that walke <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap>ly. 2. Theſſ 3. 6.</item>
                           <item>3 That it is the honor of Princes not to correct the doings of their godly aunceſtors, 1 Kings 12. 14. whereas the godly kings are commended for reforming not onely that which
their wicked aunceſtors brought in but alſo which their godly predoceſſors left vnreformed. 2. Chron. 35. 18. 30. 5. 2. King. 18. 4.</item>
                           <item>4 That ſuch Reformation wil be more troubleſome <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>han commodious, which declareth that theſe politiques are poſſeſſed with a lying ſpirite, for how know they that the Lord will
not geue a bleſſing of peace to his owne ordinarie. 2. Chron. 15 7. Againe, what deuill taught them that greater trouble then commoditie would be in ſeruing God, as through the
abandoning of euill made not the troubles ſuſteyed therein great commodities and bleſſings to him that ſuffered them.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Miniſters
he moueth ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rantes
to draw them
back,
<list>
                           <item>1 By accuſing them to be peſtulent and ſeditions fellowes, and mainteyners of fortes. Actes 24. 5. Heretiques. Actes 24. 14.
<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> perſons. Ierem. 15. 10. troublers oft eſtate. 1. Kings 18. 17.</item>
                           <item>2 By impriſoning them. Ierem 20. 2. and threatning them with death except they ceaſe Exod. 10. 28. 2. Chron. 25. 16. Iere.
11. 21. yea many times ſlaying ſome of them to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> other from following the worke of the Lord.</item>
                           <item>3 By cauſing their frends to forſake them. Tit. 4. 10. 16.
<list>
                                 <item>Al theſe things being promoters of the miniſters
bleſſednes. Mat. 5. ought to make them more bold and
forwarde in the worke. Actes 9. 21. Actes 13. 45. 46.
Philip. 1. 14. knowing that the Lord will aſſiſt them.
Tit. 4. 17.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 The peple
whom he ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth
to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
alſo
<list>
                           <item>1 By vpbrayding them with lack of learning and knowledge. Iohn 7. 40.</item>
                           <item>2 By cauſing tyrants to oppreſſe them by all vngodlymenes. Exod. 5. 6. 7. 8.</item>
                           <item>3 By ſending out falſe teachers to withdraw them.
<list>
                                 <item>Againſt all which the people muſt arme themſelues with knowledge and patience, not forſaking the
worke of the Lord for any thing.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>7 The ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
&amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
(after the
hinderances
therof ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come)
wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
we are to
know,
<list>
                     <item>1 The
pointes &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of this
ſolemnitie,
which are
<list>
                           <item>1 A gathering together of all the ſtates of that place where the reformation is to be made. 2. Kings 23. 1. 2. Nehe. 8. 1.</item>
                           <item>2 A faithfull laying open of the word by preaching in the cares of them all, that they may ſee where reformation wanteth. 2. Chron. 34. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>0. Nehem. 8. 4. 8.</item>
                           <item>3 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> prayer, with prayſing of God for his godnes in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> them a ſight of their wants, and a way to reforme them, with humble confeſſion of their former rebellions,
diſobediences, and backſlidings. Nehem. 8. 6. to the end.</item>
                           <item>4 A ſolemne couenant to be made with God by the whole ſtate. 2. Kings 11. 17. 2 Chron. 15. 14. 15. In which couenant they promiſe hence forwarde to forſake all their own ways
and intentions, and to cleaue to the commandments of God alone. Vnto this promiſe was adioyned an oath, and a curſe or deſire of vengeance to come vpon themſelues, if they
forſake the wayes of the Lord for any other 2. Kings 11. 17. Nehem. 10, 29.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
why ſuch
maner of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiuing
this
reformation
is needfull,
which are,
<list>
                           <item>1 Becauſe in a publique deformation of the Church the couenant of our peace is generally broken: wherefore it behoueth vs in returning and reforming our ſelues, to renewe the
ſame couenant, as generally, and that in as ſolemne maner as may be, ſeeing we are to deale, not with earth and aſhes, but with the God of infinite maieſtie, with whom to deale
in light and diſſolute manner, eſpecially in ſuch a worke, were great ſinne.</item>
                           <item>2 Becauſe of the commandement of the Lord, who in the publique rebellion of Prince and people, chargeth them which are in authoritie with that people, not only to receiue inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
to reioyce before the Lord in trembling, &amp;c. but moreouer requireth of them and theirs, a ſolemne couenant, and the outward teſtimonie of it, if they wil auoyde the anger of
God. Pſalme 2.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>8 The frutes
&amp; bleſſinges
which folow
the receuers
&amp; workers
of this refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation.
the Lord alwais
geueth a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
vnto it 2. Chron.
15. 7. Forhe
<list>
                     <item>1 Heareth the voice of ſuch, and their prayer commeth vp into hearin, to his holy habitation.
2. Chron. 30. 27.</item>
                     <item>2 Forgeueth their former tranſgreſſions, and though they were is red as crimſen, or ſcarlet,
he maketh them as white as ſnow or wooll. Eſay. 1. 18. 19.</item>
                     <item>3 Cauſeth them to dwell in their own land, and not to remoue. Ierem. 4. 1. 7. 3.</item>
                     <item>4 Maketh them to eate the good of the land. Eſay 1. 19. 62. 89. yea he openeth the windowes
of heauen, and powreth down vpon them the bleſſings of the earth in aboundance. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach.
3. 10.</item>
                     <item>5 Geueth them reſt and quietnes from their enemies. 2. Kings 11. 20. 2. Chron. 14. 5. 15.
15. 19. 20. 30. Eſay 31. 7. 8. 9.</item>
                     <item>6 Geueth them ſtrange victories, and mighty great ſpoyles of their enemies. 2. Chron. 14. 12
15. 15. 2. 20. 14. 23.</item>
                     <item>7 Maketh them to rule ouer many nations, &amp; ſuffereth not other to raigne ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Deu. 15. 6.</item>
                     <item>8 Maketh at things to proſper that they take in hand. 2. Kings 18. 7.</item>
                     <item>9 Geueth to that Prince honor &amp; riches in aboundance, eſtabliſhing the kingdome in his hand
2. Chron. 17. 5.
<list>
                           <item>Theſe and infinite bleſſinges follow this Reformation, wherefore they that wilfully withſtande it
euidently declare, that they ſeeke not the wealth, peace, plentie, godly preheminence, and flouriſhing
eſtate of their Prince and Countrey.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
